Functions are a way to help us organize our code in a way that is reusable.
It lets us accept our humans.
Like we saw earlier on in the class that also lets us provide defaults we're needed.
And loops let us take actions on collections of items that we've built up,
our lists, our dictionaries, or tuples.
And then we can use Boolean logic to control the flow of the program.
Now, we've been working in the Rebels so far.
It's time to move on to working in Python files.
We want to be able to save and reuse and run again.
So if you need to create a Python file, it ends in a .py extension.
There are some naming conventions that you can find in Pepe 8 guidelines.
But for the most part, Python file names should be all in lower case.
They should be separated.
The word should be separated with underscores.
Found names should be as short as possible.
And they should end in .py.
We're going to talk about modules a little bit later.
But you don't want to, it's called smurf name, your files.
So you don't want to say my underscore lib APIs.
My underscore lib helpers.
My underscore lib utilities.
Instead, you would put all of those in a folder called my lib.
And just name them the simple file names.
Just APIs.
Just exceptions.
Just blog.py.
Here are some bad example file names.
Don't name your Python files and all caps.
Don't use camel case.
So capitalizing the first letter of each word.
That is the best practice or standard from a different programming language.
And don't use smurfy really underscore long descriptive project file name.py.
You might see .py files in your directory as you start running your Python projects.
Those are compiled intermediary Python files.
They are for optimization.
You don't have to worry about them.
But you do need to be careful about not committing them to get.
So those PIC files are just, they don't matter.
They don't need to be included with your program.
And sometimes, stale versions of these files can cause problems.
For example, if you're checking out a different branch and get and your PIC files don't really match.
So if you're running into weird problems when working with Python files,
you can use this command on Mac or Linux to find all of those PIC files and just blow them away all at once.
We already saw how to run Python programs from VS code and how to create new Python files.
If you want to run that same file from your terminal, you just need to make sure that you have your virtual environment activated.
And let's see what I have in this file.
So again, when your virtual environment is activated, you can just use Python.
Not Python 3 or Python 3.9.
Python is the executable in your virtual environment that you know maps to the right place.
And then you would just pass in the file name.
Or in VS code.
We would want to make sure to exit our REPL.
And then do run Python file in terminal.
And that will go ahead and do the same thing.
So those are the different options.
Once we move on to files, remember earlier I said that the REPL when you type a variable or string.
It'll just show you the value right then and there.
That functionality does not exist in files.
So if you want to see the output in Python files, you're going to need to start putting print statements in them.
So make sure that you print the values of your strings if you want to see them.
If not, that's totally fine as well.
You can have print statements in while you debug and then comment them out once your program is ready.
Or once you start writing more advanced programs, you might use the logger module, which lets you configure how output from your Python program is presented.
That is outside of the scope of the course.
So I won't be covering it today.
So if you're going to be sharing your code with a team or you plan on sharing it or you're working in production, you generally don't want to leave print statements littered in your code.
Those are for your own debugging.
So something to be mindful of.
Output formatting tips remember earlier showed you the backslash n signified in new line backslash t is for tab.
You can use the special control characters for your advantage when you're printing stuff out and you want to make sure that it is readable.
You can also pretty print with something called the pretty print module.
And I want to show that too quickly because I find it super useful.
So opening up my repo here.
I'm going to create a long list.
If I tried to print this, it's not very readable.
Pretty print is included in the Python standard library.
So I can say from paperint import paperint.
And that will let me access this module.
Because paperint is not one of those built in functions that we saw.
It's not Len.
It's not print where we can just use it without importing it.
This is kind of a special case.
And once you have imported it, we can pass in the long list here and it will go ahead and print it out with line breaks.
So if you're looking at complex code, this is a great tool to use to make it more human readable.